[Music]
Hey Nick, how are you doing? Pretty
good. How about yourself? Yes, all good.
Thank you so much. Um, thank you for
joining uh the conference. uh really
excited to have uh you share with us
your expertise on how to build a GitHub
compiler extension. Um I'll just preface
this by saying that Nick is a developer
advocate at Polarium and and is pretty
much an expert uh in the open source and
zero trust space. Um so that said, let's
with that said, let's uh I'll switch it
to you Nick. Okay,
perfect. Cool. Awesome. Hey everybody,
thanks for joining. So yeah, so today
we're gonna create a GitHub copilot
extension. Uh I've given this talk uh a
few times. Sometimes it's an hour,
sometimes it's 30 minutes. This is the
first time doing it. 15 minutes, so
which is totally fine, but uh you know,
we're gonna not speedrun, but uh we're
we're gonna we're gonna get to it. Okay.
All right. Would help if I'm on the
right screen clicking button. So uh I
won't intro myself again. Uh B already
did that. But here's all the places you
can find me. Uh
nikkiet.online has all my links. Uh from
Montreal, Quebec, Canada. So if you like
poutine, you are my
friend. So uh you know before we get
into what is a GitHub co-pilot
extension, I'll just talk briefly about
GitHub copilot. Uh probably most of you
have heard of it. Um if you haven't,
it's like a coding assistant that is
more than just a coding assistant. They
have like an agent mode where it can
keep iterating on things now these days.
But the interesting about GitHub copilot
is like many of you probably use VS
Code. It's available in there, but it's
actually also available on github.com.
If you're a net developer, it's
available in uh Visual Studio. Uh also,
if you are a uh a developer for iOS
apps, it's actually available in Xcode
as well. Now uh there's a CLI for it and
uh they released a whole SDK uh so that
you can actually implement uh co-pilot
in any editor now. So I know Jetrains
has this as well but if you wanted to
create an editor if you're that
ambitious you can go ahead and add
C-pilot to it. Um so that's just a
little preamble about GitHub Copilot but
let's talk about what a GitHub copilot
extension
is. So the name kind of says it all. It
literally extends GitHub copilot. Um, so
you can create custom AI powered tools.
You can integrate with thirdparty
services. Uh, you can also access files
in editor
context. There's two types of co-pilot
extensions. There's one that's a skill
set and this is like uh makes it easy to
connect thirdparty services and custom
APIs into the co-pilot workflow. You can
think of those like tools. And there's
also this agent mode and that's the one
we're going to go through today. um we
don't have time to build out one of
each. Um and the agent just provides
complete control over the whole request
response within a GitHub co-pilot
session. Um and you can enable custom
workflows. You can connect to other LLMs
APIs and have access to the entire
conversation context and user
interactions. That sounds pretty fancy
the way I said that, but basically it
knows what files you're working with if
you allow that permission. And you can
kind of get the message history as
well. And the cool thing about the
extensions are they pretty much work
everywhere that GitHub Copilot is. So I
mentioned github.com. You can actually
use it there. You could use a Visual
Studio or VS Code, etc., etc. The only
place it's not available at the moment
copilot extensions is in the co-pilot ex
uh the co GitHub copilot CLI as far as I
know. Uh cool. Uh, I'm just going to
switch over to the comments for a sec
just so I can see what's going on. Cool.
Um, yeah. So, one interesting thing is,
you know, security is important. So, the
first time you interact with a co-pilot
extension,
um, you know, oh, that's the wrong
slide. Sorry. U,, this is kind of what
it looks like when you first start off.
So, if you want to use a co-pilot
extension, you'll have like your chat
area for copilot. And you have to
actually start off with at and the name
of the copilot extension and then
whatever your question is or whatever
you're trying to do. Uh if you actually
say something like hey GitHub
copilot at lama copilot memoize this
function it's actually just going to use
copilot itself and not the extension. So
you just have to remember whenever you
want to leverage a co-pilot extension,
you always have to start it with at
whatever the co-pilot extension is and
then what you're trying to
do. Cool. All right. So let's just talk
a bit about the anatomy of a co-pilot
extension.
Now, I will preface this with uh Visual
Studio Code specifically, at least when
I looked at this last year, has GitHub
Copilot extensions that are specific to
uh Visual Studio Code. I'm not going to
focus on those today, uh just for time
reasons. But also, uh I actually like
the the more general C-pilot extension
because this can be used everywhere. And
basically what you need to have a
working co-pilot extension is you need a
publicly accessible web application or
something that can serve endpoints.
That's number one. The other thing is
you need to register a GitHub
application. And those things together
with whatever permissions you decide to
set is what compromises a copilot
extension. And the bare bones
permissions. And I'll I'll I'll show you
this in a bit, but basically the minimal
thing you need to have for it to
actually work as a co-pilot extension is
you have to give access to the user's
co-pilot chat uh history. And this is
read only and it's required and there's
no write mode. It's only always read
only. That's the bare bones one. If you
want to have access to like the context
of the editor like what files are being
edited, etc., You also have to add the
context uh permission which is also read
only. Now when you're interacting with a
copilot extension the first time you ask
it about something where you might be
referencing an uh a file for example
here I have
index.ts it's going to ask me uh you
know can can I actually access your
context. So saying I would like to read
your active file and selection. Uh so
initially it says it failed to give me a
401. I have to allow it and I can allow
it for the specific project I'm in or I
can allow for all workspaces if you're
just like yolo let's do this. Um and
that's just a nice thing. You just don't
want it all of a sudden just reading
stuff without you knowing that it didn't
that it was doing that. So that's a
little bit of security there. Just take
a quick sip of
water. Okay. Yeah, I'm just looking in
the chat. There's extensions transform
copilot from a code assistant into a
developer workflow engine. Yeah, it's
pretty cool. Yeah, stay staying
hydrated, B. Thanks. Cool. So, for
getting your development in environment
set up, uh you know, we just need to
install the dependencies of this
template that I'll show you in a second.
Uh we also need to expose the local
development server to the internet. I'll
show you how to do that as well. and we
need to create and configure a GitHub
application. We're also going to
leverage the Copilot extension preview
SDK and I'll show you how you can debug
the
extension. One thing I'll mention about
C-Pilot extensions
is right now with the preview SDK, it's
specific to JavaScript TypeScript, but a
C-pilot extension that serves endpoints,
it can be literally in any language. be
Go, Elixir, I don't know, Assembly if
you're ambitious maybe. Uh, but at the
time, uh, for the time being, as far as
I know, there's only a preview SDK for
all things JavaScript. Um, but that
said, you know, it's open source. If
you're interested in like leveraging
your own language to leverage what's in
the preview SDK, you could always uh
maybe use Copilot to port it to another
language. So, we're going to go ahead
and take a uh do the demo here now, but
I just want to show you this is the
template I'm using. So, this is uh my
GitHub copilot extension template. Um
feel free to give it a star if you'd
like to. This is like uh JavaScript
JavaScript based project. It's
leveraging the preview SDK and it's just
like a bare bones to kind of get you up
and running. Um, for the sake of time,
I'm going to show you a co-pilot
extension I built with it, but I'm going
to talk through the pieces in it. All
right, so immediately sharing this. All
right, awesome. Cool. So, let's go ahead
and move over to the editor. And I know
some people are probably going to say,
light mode, my eyes, but uh I find I
live stream a lot and I find uh light
mode actually works better for uh
sharing screens and stuff. Okay, so
let's back up a bit here. Okay, that's
the debug environment, but let's go back
to here for a second and let's go
through what you need to do to actually
configure the GitHub copilot extension
uh from the GitHub app perspective. So,
you want to go to your settings and then
you come down here and it's developer
settings. And I'll zoom this in a bit.
You can see uh I've I've done this a few
times. Uh I'm just going to walk you
through the what you need to have here.
So this is the one we're going to demo.
So I've already created it, but
essentially when you go to create it,
it's the same kind of flow. There's a
few things here and the required field.
So you have to give it a name. So I call
it the product manager. Spoiler alert,
we have a copilot extension that's going
to be a product manager for us. And when
you actually reference it in the copilot
chat, this name is what's going to be
used, but it'll be like at
the-rmgr for example. Um, oh, cool.
Thanks for sharing the template. Um, so
you need to have a name obviously. Uh
the homepage URL, I'm using the same URL
that I'm using as the endpoints that I'm
going to be using in Copilot. But if
this was like you're deploying this to
production, you would probably have like
a branded page on your website or maybe
it's part of the Copilot extension. For
now, it's a required field. So I'm just
putting it there. So like if I come to
this, you should see Okay. Yeah, I have
to say continue. Uh but you can see here
it just says welcome to the co-pilot
extension template. That's that's my
branding. Um, but let's close that. Um,
the other things just to note, uh, you
need to add a callback URL even if
you're not using OOTH. Um, I hung out
with a bunch of the folks from GitHub at
one point to go through this when this
came out last summer. And this is
apparently still a required field even
though it's not used. So, you just fill
it in. I just put the same URL. I think
from a UX perspective, they're going to
they're going to ask that at some point
if you're using a Copilot extension. um
do not have a web hook active and that's
pretty much all you need to do
there. And then let's talk about
permissions. So I mentioned before, so
we need account
permissions. So at a minimum, you need
this co-pilot chat and you need to have
it set to read only. There's only two
options, no access or readon. Without
this one, it's just not going to work. I
have this other one also added and this
is so I can get access to the editor
context. This one is optional. It
depends what you're doing with your
extension. So those two things there.
And then we come to this new tab that's
been in I guess GitHub apps for about a
year maybe. And by default it's select
it's set at disabled. We want it as
agent for this particular one. But you
can also do skill set which I mentioned
which is kind of like a bunch of tools
that copilot can access. We're going to
focus on the agent one. And then
basically the main thing is we need to
have an endpoint here and this is where
your extension is actually going to like
from GitHub copilot. Copilot is going to
do a form post to this URL and then you
know I just have like what is what is
this extension and I say you are a wacky
project manager that you know suggests
wacky humorous product feature ideas. Uh
you kind of get the idea. So it's a bit
of a spoiler. Um, okay. Let's go ahead
here and move over here now. So, uh, the
other thing I want to talk about is we
have the preview SDK stuff. I'm using
some nice features in here. So, they
have all these helper functions. So, you
can say like create an acknowledge
event. Um, what this does is when the
request comes in, it will notify the
co-pilot UI that like okay, something's
happening. And then you'll see like the
UI adjust to show that something's
happening. And when you're done whatever
your request was, you can say done and
that'll notify the co-pilot UI to just
say like stop spinning or stop doing
what you're doing. And there's some
other nice things here. You can get like
the user message, which is the the
latest question you ask or the latest
prompt. Um there's some security
features to verify and parse the request
to make sure you know it's still an
endpoint so people can actually post to
it. So, you know, there's that, too. I'm
using Hano. Again, you don't have to use
this. This is just what I decided to go
with the template. Now, a few things to
notice here. Uh, I'm just going to stop
this for a second. We need, as I
mentioned, we need to make this publicly
accessible on the internet. So, I'll
drop this in the chat, but if all of you
go to, well, not not all of you. Well,
it doesn't matter, I guess, but if you
go to this URL I just posted in the
comments, you should be okay. I can't
post it. Uh oh, there it goes. Uh you
should be able to go to that URL and you
should see like a welcome to the Copilot
extension. Uh the way I do that, and
there's many tools you can use to do
this, but since I'm in VS Code most of
the time, I basically go with the
built-in stuff, they have port
forwarding. So, I've decided to port
forward port 3000, which is what my web
app is running on. And I'm just going to
make it public. By default, it's
private. And those are the two criteria
there. Now, I'm just going to go ahead
and start the dev server. I've got the
debugger running here, too. And on the
right here, I'm going to ask a question.
Well, I'm going to say like at the
product manager slashfeature because I
want it to give me a new
feature. And this is going to start
thinking. Okay. And now we're in the
debugger here. And this might time out
because I'm in here, but uh basically
there's some security checks. So, I'm
checking if it's a valid request. It is.
It verified the payload that came in. So
there's like special headers from GitHub
to just verify the authenticity. That's
a nice out of the box thing. Let's go
ahead and let it run. And so what this
extension does is it's just going to
create a wacky product idea. So uh I was
talking to my friend Gant Labour because
I give this talk at All Things OpenAI
and he's like, "Love the talk, but it'd
be cool if you had like a wacky
extension." And so I decided to make the
the crazy uh product man not crazy
product manager but wacky ideas product
manager. So says sure introduce the
procrastinators pause button and I can
give feedback on this. So let's say like
awesome
uh let's only let them press it every
five minutes. So now I'm interacting
with the co-pilot extension. I'm going
to detach here uh just so that it can
run and we can close the side panel here
just to get a bit more real estate. This
is running on my local machine so it
could be a little slower but you can see
here it's I'm interacting with it. It's
suggested like okay that's great. Let's
add the five minutes and stuff. So okay
at this point I'm like okay I'm pretty
happy with that. So I'm going to say
slashdone.
Now I'm like, this is a great idea.
Perfect. Okay. Now, the nice thing here
is I just got a prompt. And this is
actually another thing that comes with
the preview SDK. I can actually output
instructions for Copilot to give me a
prompt. So, I'm going to say, do I want
to generate a products requirements
document? And you can say yes or no. I'm
going to say yes, uh, just to show the
rest of what I did here. And this is a
goofy demo, I know, but I was thinking
about it after I built this demo. This
could actually be very valuable as a
real PRD generator, just not with wacky
ideas. And so I'm able to just generate
this and this is like a way for me to
extend GitHub Copilot with something
bespoke that I needed, you know, cuz
like who doesn't need a a wacky product
manager coming up with uh wild ideas?
But you can see it it took our whole
discussion. It consolidated into like
what the core of the idea is. It took my
suggestions in there and then it talks
about the requirements. And so that's
pretty cool. Um uh we still got a little
bit of time before we get to Q&A, but I
just kind of want to show you like those
other neat things here. So we're
streaming the event. So this is the
acknowledge. So this is what allows
C-pilot to just start that spinner or
whatever the UI is because it's
different depending if you're on like
github.com or GitHub copilot. And then
you can see here I just have this
template. I did this all in line. That's
generally probably not a best approach
in terms of like if you're programming
something, but this is a a small demo.
Uh, but basically I've I've just have
this kind of hash table of like all the
brainstorming sessions and the ideas and
then I just generate it in there and put
it in a nice way, you know, and then I
do some cleanup if there's markdown and
stuff. That's a TypeScript error that I
guess I need to fix, but you know, I'll
get um we got about a minute here left,
but uh so this is what's nice. So like
this create confirmation event. So like
let's just do this again real quick. I'm
going to say
feature. Oh, I actually have to start
the dev server again. Sorry. This is
going to probably stop in a sec. Let's
do another one. And let's do
slashfeature. And I think it'll hit that
break point. Yes, it did. Okay. Let's
just click play. Okay. And it's going to
go ahead and do its thing. It's going to
give us a wacky idea again. I'm just
going to get rid of this one.
Now again it's it's my own website
running on my local machine that
GitHub's interacting with or GitHub
copilot. Okay, I'm gonna say slashdone
again. And this is where we should see a
breakpoint if I put it in the right
place. Yes, I did. Okay, so where where
did it go? Uh here. There we go. You can
see here I've created the confirmation
event and just let it run. I'll detach
here because I know we're at time. But
then you're gonna see the prompt and I'm
just gonna say accept. And there we go.
Hey Bob.
Amazing. Thank you so much. Like
extremely insightful session. Uh and
also I I want to say like that template
is a little gem. Like um I was trying to
click on it but I think it doesn't allow
me to. But you definitely I owe you a
star for sure. Okay. Cool. Cool. Thanks
man. Yeah. Yeah. Um now uh the one thing
is and this is why we didn't want to
stop you because this was like extremely
valuable but um we've run out of the Q&A
uh time. However, like um I mean no no
problem there because I think uh the the
last minutes were were really important,
right? Especially to to close it up. Uh
now to the audience, if there's anyone
who wants to follow up, uh please go
start the repo by the way. It looks
really cool. Uh but if you want to
follow up on uh on on this with Nick uh
please reach out to him. Um and yeah,
just wanted to personally thank you for
uh this uh practical uh live demo. Cool.
Thanks, Bob. And thanks everybody.